A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Policy and Planning, Office Files of Eugene S. Staples FA675
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Policy and Planning, Office Files of Eugene S. Staples
1963-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Staples, Eugene S.
Ford Foundation
FA675
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
Arrangement
As received.
Scope and Contents
Memoranda, reports and general files.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Biographical / Historical
Eugene "Rocky" Staples was a foundation program officer and executive, journalist, diplomat, and World War II veteran. He held numerous positions at the Ford Foundation between 1964 and 1981, primarily concerned with the Foundation's Asia programming. In 1992, he helped found the Eurasia Foundation, and he served as President of that organization until his retirement in 1997.
Staples joined the Ford Foundation in 1964 as Associate Director of Policy and Planning. In 1966, he started his work with the Foundation's Asia programs as Deputy Director of South and Southeast Asia. He occupied a number of different positions in the succeeding years. Some of his position title changes reflect the Foundation's reorganization and retitling of its programming for Asia. For example, he was Head of South and Southeast Asia and then Head of Asia and Pacific. In 1973, he became the Foundation's Representative for Southeast Asia, and in 1976, he became the Foundation's Representative for India, Nepal, and Sri Lanka. He stayed in that last position until he left the Foundation in 1981. The Foundation later commissioned Staples to write a brief history about the Foundation's history of programming in India. Staples' volume, "Forty Years: A Learning Curve, The Ford Foundation in India, 1952-1992" was published in 1992.
Prior to joining the Ford Foundation, Staples had a career in journalism and diplomacy as a United Press correspondent in Mexico, a United States Foreign Service press officer in Uruguay and Chile, and Cultural Counselor at the U.S. Embassy in Moscow, Russia. He also served as a U.S. Marine Corps fighter pilot in World War II.
After leaving the Ford Foundation, Staples joined the United States Agency for International Development (USAID) in 1981. He served in Pakistan from 1985 until he left the organization in 1988. Then, from 1992 to 1997, he served as President of the Eurasia Foundation which he helped establish.
Staples' education focused on foreign language learning. Fluent in Spanish and Russian, he graduated from the English-language Mexico City College and did advanced Russian language studies through the State Department and U.S. Army. Staples died in 2013.
- General Memoranda -- Negro -- File I, 1963-1965 (Box 1)
- General Memoranda -- Negro -- File II, 1966 (Box 1)
- Interview Memoranda -- Negro -- File I, 1965 April-June (Box 1)
- Interview Memoranda -- Negro -- File II, 1965 July-December (Box 1)
- Interview Memoranda -- Negro -- File III, 1966 (Box 1)
- Minority Problems Committee -- General, 1966 (Box 1)
- Negro Education Meeting -- Greyston Conference Center, 1963 September 12-13 (Box 1)
- Negro -- Ford Foundation Grants and Projects related to Development of the American Negro, 1966 (Box 1)
- Reports, 1964-1967 (Box 1)
- Negro Committee -- General, 1966 (Box 2)
- Informational Data and Miscellaneous Reports, 1963 (Box 2)
- Informational Data and Miscellaneous Reports, 1964-1965 (Box 2)
- Informational Data and Miscellaneous Reports, 1966 (Box 2)